# 你看看都烤成腰圆似的
See? Their shapes are like kidney
# 这一切渣儿都掉下来了
The fragments are falling off when you cut it
# 我们做什么都得规矩
We need to stick to the rules whatever we do
# 有的就胡乱扔
Some people tend to throw them everywhere
# 这个特别规矩就不一样了
It will be totally different if you stick to the rules
# 就这烧饼我们谁也没敢接
Neither of us dared teach how to make this pancake
# 做不出来怕不行
We were afraid of making a bad example
# 必须等您来
So we must wait for you
# 今天根据现有的条件
Today we will make use of what we have here
# 就让网友们能在家制作 现在开始
To show everyone how to make it at home. Let's get started now
# 我们把半斤的面粉倒入这里头
Let's pour half jin (250 g) of flour into this (bowl)
# 搁的中筋面
We are using plain flour here
# 四克的酵母  两克的泡打粉
Add 4 grams of yeast,  2 grams of baking powder
# 二十克的白糖搁在里头
and 20 grams of sugar into the bowl
# 那么热的天搁凉水就可以了
Now it's hot, so we add cold water
# 冬天可以搁点温水
In winter, you can add warm water instead
# 我们这水搁的是一百五十克
Here we add 150 grams of water
# 不能一次加满
But you cannot add it one-off
# 有的面粉干湿度也不太一样
The humidity of flours may also differ
# 王师傅在这个行业里边
Master Wang is definitely
# 是正经八百的国宝级大师
a national-treasure-level master in this profession
# 在《舌尖3》里边有王师傅的镜头
He showed up in the season 3 of 'A Bite of China'
# 大爷您知道吗
Da Ye, do you know
# 为什么我跟王师傅非常亲
why I have a very close relationship with Master Wang
# 您知道为什么么
Do you know why?
# 王师傅跟我师父是一个单位的
Master Wang worked at the same place as my master did
# 以后你就别当大爷了
In the future, you may not be 'Da Ye' anymore
# 大大爷这儿有了 你拍二大爷
We have a 'Da Da Ye' (literally elder Da Ye) here. You will be 'Er Da Ye' (secondary Da Ye)
# 这个面活好了之后
When the dough is kneaded well
# 咱们就饧一会儿 十五分钟
Let it rest for a while. 15 minutes
# 主要的关键得有酥层
The key of this snack is the 'crispy layers'
# 就必须得烫油酥
So you must prepare 'You Su'
# 开酥都是用素油是吧 对
-We use vegetable oil when making 'You Su'? -Yep
# 这个就行了 稍微晾一晾
This temperature is ok. Cool it down a bit
# 这时候再和 慢点儿啊
-Now mix it up. -Be careful
# 到这个程度就行了
It's done when it looks like this
# 拿过来咱们就揉
We can start kneading the dough when taking it out
# 刚才不太光溜 一定揉滋润了
It was not smooth enough just now. We must knead it until smooth
# 其实有好多面都必须得二次饧
In fact, we need to rest the dough twice in many cases
# 稍微再等一会儿 马上就开始了
Rest it for a while again. We can start soon
# 饧十分钟 什么都在饧
Rest it for 10 minutes. Resting is a very important process in pastry
# 不管蒸馒头 其实这个过程很重要
No matter what you make, for example, steamed bread. This process is essential
# 这过程大家一会儿看
This process... Let's wait and see
# 这个饧的差不多了
The resting is almost complete
# 这个面胀起来了
The dough is now swelling
# 铺点干面 咱们给它开长
Sprinkle some dry flour and let's roll the dough
# 越擀的薄层次不就越多么
The thinner you roll it, the more layers you'll get
# 我们做什么都得规矩
We need to stick to the rules whatever we do
# 别给弄成这弧太大就不好看
Don't make it too round, that'll be ugly
# 已经擀成这样之后 把油酥抹上
After rolling it like this, smear the 'You Su'
# 抹匀 要有刮板就好了 就一下就刮平了
Smear it evenly. It'd be good if we have a scraper, which'll do the job at once
# 刮匀完了之后撒点干面 这也是一小技巧
After smearing, sprinkle some dry flour. This is also a trick
# 一它吸收了点油
First, the dry flour absorbs some oil
# 第二层次更清晰了
Second, the layers will become clearer
# 这样弄完了之后就起这开始卷
Then, roll it up from here
# 卷的时候扥点儿 扥点儿层更多
Stretch it while rolling up. That'll make more layers
# 为了让它层更清晰 咱们就扥着点儿
Also stretching will make the layers clearer
# 你看看剂口让它在底下
See? Put the opening at the bottom
# 一定要让它拍一下
You must press it
# 都弄好了翻过来 手朝上
Then flip it, with your palm facing upwards
# 把这个掐上 排成队
Hold it tight and nip it off. Put these pieces in a line
# 有的就胡乱扔 这样养成的毛病就不好
Some people tend to throw them everywhere. That's a bad habit
# 剂口朝上一会你操作也好找
With the opening facing upwards, it'll be easy for you to find it in later steps
# 不给你找麻烦
It won't cause you trouble
# 这个就是剂口 剂子的口
This is the opening. The opening of this piece
# 我们做的时候要这样给它弄好
When processing the dough pieces, do it this way
# 你看把这个收好口
See? Hide the opening inside
# 这样就行了
This is done.
# 要如果不找这剂口 你给搁外头
If you fail to find the opening, like, leave it outside
# 就脑门子都开了 崩了
The whole piece will be broken
# 一定把三个口都给它掩到中间
You must close the three openings in the middle
# 表面光滑了 收在一起
Such that the surface can be smooth and tidy
# 这才行 跟挤饺子似的
That's the standard. This is like making a dumpling
# 你看我发现大大爷一来 大爷就是歇菜
I notice that when Da Da Ye is here, Da Ye becomes silent
# 我在耐心地学习
I'm also learning patiently
# 你看看 不光网友能学东西
It's true that, not only our audience can learn something
# 我们也学了好多
We've also learned a lot
# 王师傅这回去我就能做了
Master Wang, I can make this myself now at home
# 但是没您做的好 我也能照猫
But not as good as yours. I can 'draw a tiger by looking at a cat'
# 这词儿用的不当啊
That's not the proper way of using this phrase
# 比着葫芦画瓢 这段话掐了啊
-You should say 'draw a ladle by looking at a gourd'. -Let's delete this sentence from the video
# 在家要做特别好做
It is very easy to make this at home
# 愿意弄咸的 撒些椒盐也好吃
If you prefer salty ones, you can adding some pepper salt. It'll also be delicious
# 一定擀成腰圆似的饼
You must roll the dough into the shape of a kidney
# 你们要喜欢圆的也行  这个就是好看
It's ok if you like circular ones. This (shape) looks good.
# 这个网友要好好照您这学 真能学会
If our audience learns carefully from you, they'll master it
# 这没问题 这回去就能立竿见影
No problem. You'll be able to make it yourself
# 整个的坯子弄完了
The base doughs are ready
# 刷蛋液 我们是刷全蛋液
Smear some yolk-white mixture. Mixed whole egg
# 要颜色感 好看
That gives the beautiful color
# 这样做完了之后
After this step
# 我还告诉网友们 一定要把这个蘸上
Let me tell you guys. You must dip this
# 也一再告诉我们徒弟
I've also been telling my apprentices
# 有的时候蘸上就直接搁上了
If you start baking directly after dipping the sesames
# 这时候就滋滋剌剌的
They'll be uneven while baking
# 看着表皮就不好看
The surface will be ugly
# 我们一定要把这个研一下
We must flatten it here
# 你看在这研一下 特别平
See? Just flatten it. It'll be very flat
# 特别规矩就不一样了
It'll be totally different if you strictly stick to the rules
# 就这一个动作 师父要不给讲
Just a simple step like this. If your master doesn't teach you...
# 这个我劝大家不管做什么都得做细
Here I would urge everyone to be careful with whatever you do
# 这个是生芝麻 烤得了芝麻还不容易掉
We are using raw sesame. They won't fall off after baking
# 你看这个特别平整 大小均匀这样就行了
These are so flat and tidy, and uniform in size. That's ok
# 看着那么薄
Now they are very thin
# 一定让它胀起将近一倍来 再去烤
You must start baking after it swells up to twice its volume
# 要进五十度的温度的炉温
They should be put into the oven at 50 degrees Celcius
# 现在这饧着 行 这有五十度
Now let them rest here. Ok, this is 50 degrees Celcius
# 大家看一看 饧了十几分钟之后
See? After resting for about 10 minutes
# 已经胀起来了
They've already swelled up
# 在饧发的当中就不能乱磕了
During resting, you shouldn't bump it
# 如果啪这一磕
If the cake is bumped
# 它蹲下去 就再不起了
It will collapse and never return to the original shape
# 一会儿把炉温升到二百五十度
Later let's raise the oven temperature to 250 degrees Celcius
# 底火咱们可以搁二百二 一百八也行
The bottom heat can be set to 220 or 180 degrees Celcius
# 上火搁二百五
The top heat should be set to 250 degrees Celcius
# 因为小的（烤箱）就二百三十度
This small oven can only be set to 230 degrees Celcius at most
# 二百三会不会影响到
Will this temperature have a negative effect?
# 它就是上颜色慢 不能让它炕干了
It's just slower. However we can't let it become too dry
# 急火让它快烤 颜色金黄色
If we bake it at higher temperature, it'll be golden yellow
# 吃起来特别外头酥 里头绵软
The outer surface will be crispy while the inside is soft and tender
# 一定温度得升好了 二百三十度
The temperature must be raised properly (before baking). 230 degrees Celcius now
# 十五分钟到二十分钟 十五分钟吧
-15 minutes to 20 minutes. -15 minutes
# 如果要真是火急 看着有颜色了就ok了
If the heat is powerful enough, it'll be ok when it turns golden yellow
# 因为它是发面的东西 特别柔软
Because this is a leavened pancake and is extra soft
# 我给您盯着
Let me keep an eye on the oven for you
# 芝麻金黄 好 没问题
Golden sesames. Ok, there's no problem
# 一个一个给它敲敲 都动了
Knock them one by one. They are falling off
# 你看看都烤成腰圆似的 中间来一个
See? They are baked into the shape of kidney. Put one in the middle
# 切一个
Cut one
# 外边倍儿酥 里边绵软
The outer surface is so crispy, while the inside is very soft and tender
# 这个做完了之后
After baking
# （密封好放冰箱）搁一个星期
If you seal them properly and store in the fridge for one week
# 拿喷壶喷点 咱们再嘘一下
You can spray some water and slightly bake them again
# 还照样跟这一样
They remains the same as this
# 让网友看看你看酥不酥
Let's show our audience how crispy it is
# 这一切渣儿都掉下来了
The fragments are falling off when you cut it
# 各位网友今天做的酥层烧饼
Friends, about today's 'Crispy layered pancake'
# 这几个关键得弄好
There are a few keys you need to be careful with
# 一个是烫好油酥
First, prepare the 'You Su' properly
# 一定要擀得均匀
Also, spread the dough uniformly
# 蘸芝麻时候一定要研平
You must flatten the surface after dipping the sesame
# 你看看这特别整齐
See? It's so flat and tidy
# 关键的时候一定要把它饧发好
Most importantly, rest it well
# 饧起来 在进行烤
Let it rest until it rises up. Then start baking
# 如果饧起来往这一颠 它就不再起了
If it's bumped after rising up, it'll never return to the original shape
# 所以这几个环节 希望网友们特别注意
So these steps... I hope that you guys can pay attention to
# 还有什么要求 还有什么希望
In addition, if you have other suggestions or hopes
# 今后跟我们说
Please also tell us
# 作为我们来讲 我们只知道好吃
For us, we just know that the pancake is so delicious
# 但是我们确实没有资格评价王师傅
But we are indeed not qualified to evaluate Master Wang
# 只有膜拜了 大大爷感谢您
We can only respect him. Thank you, Da Da Ye
# 祝您老健康长寿 谢谢
-I wish you health and longevity! -Thank you!
# 一天给30块钱
(The salary was) 30 yuan per day
# 我特别的高兴
I was so excited
# 但是这个任务
But this task
# 这个活交给我了
When it was handed to me
# 我觉得我也有压力
I felt stressful as well
# 也有难度
It was also hard for me
# 为什么
Why?
# 我是一个初中的毕业生
I graduated from a middle school
# 我没有受过高等的教育
And I didn't take advanced education
# 因为我父亲对我的希望值挺大的
Since my father had a high expectation on me
# 他曾经教育我
He used to tell me that
# 就是学好数理化
'If you study math, physics, and chemistry well'
# 走遍天下都不怕
'You'll make a living wherever you are'
# 我上学
When I was a student
# 我的对数学
I was... in terms of math
# 物理
physics
# 包括化学
and chemistry
# 应该说
I would say
# 在我们学校的年级里边
In my grade
# 前十名
I was among the top 10 students
# 上班以后
After I started working
# 我还带着我的数学书
I was still keeping my math textbook
# 数学本
and math notebook
# 我想有机会
I thought that, if I had a chance
# 还应该考一个高中 上个大学
I should go to a high school and a university
# 因为这是我父亲对我的希望
Because that was my father's expectation
# 当时我刚25岁
I was just 25 years old then
# 我就觉得我在饭店里边干的
I was thinking that, when I was working in the restaurant
# 各种工作我都能干
I could do all kinds of job
# 但是我就当个老师
So it should be ok
# 也没什么不可以哈
for me to be a teacher
# 等我第一天去的时候
But when I arrived there for the first day
# 把我吓坏了
I was scared
# 42个人
There were 42 people
# 排桌排椅
Sitting in rows of desks and chairs
# 上午4节课
There were 4 classes in the morning
# 下午实操课
And practicing classes in the afternoon
# 讲什么
What should I teach?
# 我没有这方面的知识
I didn't have the systematic knowledge
# 八一年也没有更多的
in 1981, there was not many
# 烹饪的书
book about cooking
# 烹饪的资料
or anything I could refer to
# 没有
Nothing
# 全是那些老师傅言传身教
All the knowledge was passed by those old masters
# 我就读商业部
So I was reading...
# 原来出的那六本书
The six cooking books published by the Ministry of Business
# 第一节课
In the first class
# 真是我冒汗了
I was sweating
# 我备了九篇纸
I prepared nine pieces of paper
# 我也想像人家领导人
Because I also wanted to talk like the leader of the country
# 那些领导讲话似的
Or other leaders
# 说两句再发挥一下
Talk about something, and extend to something else
# 然后再看看稿
Then look at the notes
# 再发挥一下
And talk about something else
# 我怎么说我这九篇纸能坚持半天
I was like, I could definitely go through half a day with these 9 pieces of notes
# 没想到是越讲 眼睛就花了
But I didn't expect that, as I was talking, I became dazzled
# 紧张了吧
You must be nervous
# 紧张了
I became nervous
# 没东西
Because I had nothing to talk about
# 当时11月份
It was in November
# 穿了一个毛衣全湿透了
I was wearing a sweater, but it was soaked with my sweat
# 等下课的时候
When the class was going to finish
# 说下节课讲什么
I was wondering, what should I talk about in the next class?
# 干脆讲菜吧
I decided to talk about dishes directly
# 九篇纸上午就这一节课就讲完了
So I finished all my nine pieces of note in the first class
# 我觉得讲菜
I thought that talking about dishes
# 对我来讲更简单
was simpler for me
# 可是说一讲起来坏了
But when I started, it was a disaster
# 我这前言不搭后语
I couldn't be coherent
# 比如讲一个狮子头
For example, when I was talking about 'Shi Zi Tou' (braised pork ball in brown sauce)
# 讲着讲着
As I talked
# 没准讲成油焖大虾了
I might switch to 'You Men Da Xia' (braised prawns)
# 就懵了
I got lost
# 但是我最后坚持下来了
But I went on till the last
# 4节课我坚持下来了
I survived the four classes
# 这时候我才体验出
At that time, I began to realize
# 我说以前当老师有什么呀
I had thought that being a teacher was not so difficult
# 不就耍嘴吗
It's just taking, you know
# 好
Ok
# 这4节课我是一耍完嘴
When I finished my talk after the four classes
# 上气不接下气
I couldn't breathe well
# 我觉得我特别亏气
I felt I was out of breath
# 下午开始实操了
In the afternoon, the practicing started
# 实操是我的拿手好戏
I was good at practicing (compared with talking)
# 可是见了那么多人在那现场
But when I saw so many people there
# 我紧张
I became nervous
# 拿起刀来哆嗦
My hand was shaking when I held the cleaver
# 然后就故意拍那案板
So I deliberately hit the chopping board
# 下午三个菜呀
I taught three dishes in the afternoon
# 三个菜
Three dishes
# 我也坚持下来了
I survived that, too
# 通过上课
After my teaching experience
# 我发现我的缺陷不少
I realized that I had a lot of shortcomings
# 有好多知识需要去完善
and that I needed to complete a lot of knowledge
# 有的学员说
Some of my students asked
# 老师这鱼蒸多长时间
'How long should I steam the fish?'
# 我那时候没有这方面的经验
I was not experienced in this way
# 也没有这方面的总结
I didn't summarize it, either
# 我说过两天
So I said
# 我再告诉你吧
'I'll tell you in a few days'
# 说炖狮子头炖多长时间
Also, when asked "for how long should we boil 'Shi Zi Tou'"?
# 我也不清楚
I was not sure, either
# 所以从这儿
So from here
# 我就觉得这实操里边
I realized that even in my practice
# 我的缺口太大了
I still had a lot of things to learn
# 回来应该还要进一步的好好学
I should study more carefully and deeply
# 所以我回来以后
So after I returned
# 到饭店上班的时候
returned to work in the restaurant
# 把我每天所工作的这些情况
I started to make records
# 都做一些记录
of my work every day
# 比如说今天蒸个鱼
For example, if I steamed a fish
# 炖个肉
or stewed some meat
# 炒个青菜
or stir-fried some vegetable
# 我都拿笔记
I was taking notes of them
# 所以您记笔记源自于这样
So that's the origin of your notes
# 记完以后
After taking these notes
# 我觉得对我是一个很大提高
I felt that I was truly improved
# 等下一节 我就这位同学
In the next class, I told that student
# 上次你问我蒸鱼多长时间
'You asked me for how long you should steam the fish last time'
# 我今天告诉你
'This time, I can tell you'
# 蒸10分钟
'10 minutes'
# 这个10分钟是
"This '10 minutes'"
# 我准确地通过我的实践
'is precisely summarized from my practice'
# 我告诉你
'such that I tell you so'
# 那位同学炖肉
Another student might ask about stewed meat
# 比如红烧肉要炖两个小时
For example, the braised pork should be boiled for 2 hours
# 也是通过实践总结出来的
Which is also from my practice
# 这样同学对我的印象也特别好
In this way, the students began to think highly of me